Guide to the Southwestern United States photograph collection, 1893
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Southwestern United States photograph collection
1893
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives
C0201
0.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains photographs of American rail travel through the Southwestern United States in 1893.
Administrative Information
Alternative Form Available
The entire collection is available online through the Southwestern United States photograph collection.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in 2003.
Historical Information
The photographs in this collection document American travel at the turn of the century. Travel, during the latter part of the 19th century, was dominated by railroads. At the time these images were taken around 1893, over 87,801 miles of track had been laid in the United States. With the completion of the first transcontinental railroad in 1869, Americans were easily able to traverse the country facilitating the rapid settling of the Western United States.
Scope and Content
This collection documents late 19th century rail travel and the urbanization of the Southwestern United States. Images in this collection include pictures of railroad passengers and employees of differing race and social class. Also included are images of New Orleans and Southwestern towns and cities and the people who inhabited them. The photographs also document leisure travel during the 19th century and feature tourists at the seashore and several hotels.
Though many of the photographs remain unidentified, they likely feature popular tourist destinations for those traveling by rail through the Southwest. Two of the photographs depict Colorado national parks, and many depict Mission-style churches. An article pasted into the back of the original photo album suggests that many of the train photographs could have been taken on the Colorado and Southern Railway, which ran through Colorado, New Mexico, and Texas.
Arrangement
Photographs in this collection are arranged as they were in their orginal photo album. The photographs begin with images of New Orleans and illustrate travel through the Southwestern United States.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds a number of other photograph collections, including some from the late 19th century.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
New Orleans (La.)--Photographs.; Southwestern States--Photographs.
Subjects:
Architecture--Southwestern States--Photographs.; Mexican Americans--Photographs.; Railroad stations--United States--Photographs.; Railroad travel--United States--Photographs.
Document Types:
Albumen prints.
Contents List
- Southwestern United States photograph collection, 1893
  A collection of travel photographs taken in 1893. Includes images of the American Southwest and New Orleans.
  - British Freighter at Port of New Orleans, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Oyster Boats at New Orleans, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Man Reading Newspaper, Port of New Orleans, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - French Cathedral at New Orleans, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Market Scene with Young Man, New Orleans, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Market Scene with Shoppers, New Orleans, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Train Station, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Railroad Employees in Street Scene, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Railroad Employee on Train Platform I, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Railroad Employee on Train Platform II, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Desert Landscape and Village Scene, Location Unknown, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - San Xavier Hotel, Tucson, Arizona, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Street Scene with Horses and Wagon, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Horse and Buildings, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Street Scene with Mexican - American Men, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Village Scene, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - African-American Men, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - African-American Men in front of Wooden Building, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Street Scene with Mexican-American Children, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - African-American Woman with Baby in Railroad Yard, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mexican-American Women with Children, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Street scene with Mexican-American Man, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mexican-American Men at Train Station, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Side View of Building "A Turkish Bath,", 1893 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hotel I (name and location unidentified), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hotel II (name and location unidentified), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Women and Man at Seashore, Western United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Mission-Type Building, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mission Style Church, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mission Style Church, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Miracle Rock, Near the City of Grand Junction, Colorado, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Stopped Train 2 Miles Above Sea Level, Possibly Colorado, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Desert/Mountain Scene, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Desert/Mountain Scene, Southwest United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Men and Women on Train Platform, United States, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Train Employees in front of Large Building, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Photograph Album, 1893 (Box 2)
    The photographs were originally housed in this photograph album and were rehoused for preservation purposes.